Finding Aid for the Ninon MacKnight Papers LSC.0854
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ninon MacKnight papers
1942-1969
UCLA Library Special Collections
MacKnight, Ninon
LSC.0854
1 unknown (1 oversize box)
Ninon MacKnight (1908- ) drew sketches for the children's page of the Sunday Sun newspaper, and illustrated children's historical books, then illustrated picture books for younger children. Published works for which she was illustrator include Little Amish School House (1939), Snow White (c1946), For a Child: Great Poems Old and New (1947), and Kit Koala: the Shy Little Bear (c1948), which she both wrote and illustrated. The collection consists of original illustrations for seven children's books, and letters from various publishers regarding illustrations.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ninon MacKnight, 1960-85.
Gift of Paul Jordan Smith, 1971.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9922211023606533
Biography
Ninon MacKnight was born on April 5, 1908 in Sydney, Australia; attended private school for girls in Sydney; drew sketches for the children's page of the Sunday Sun newspaper; came to the United States; first illustrated children's historical books, then illustrated picture books for younger children; married Wilbur Jordan Smith; published works for which she was illustrator include Little Amish School House (1939), Snow White (c1946), For a Child: Great Poems Old and New (1947), and Kit Koala: The Shy Little Bear (c1948), which she both wrote and illustrated.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of original illustrations for seven children's books and letters from various publishers regarding illustrations.
General note
Description derived from in-house card file.
Manuscripts for publication; Illustrators -- United States -- Archives.; Juvenile literature.; Illustrated works.; Authors, American -- Archives.; MacKnight, Ninon -- Archives
- ABC of Trucks and Cars by Anne Alexander. Pictures by Ninon. Los Angeles., ca. 1956.; 19 leaves. 21.5 × 27 cm. Color dummy containing 20 original crayon drawings. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  A child's ABC book. This is the first draft of the pictures for the publisher.
  General note
  Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1956.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Gift of Mrs. Ninon MacKnight Smith, January 1960.
- Illustrations for Mr. Apple's Family, by Jean McDevitt. Los Angeles., ca. 1950.; 47 items. Original pen and watercolor drawings (various sizes). In 2 folders. (Box 1)
  Gift of Mrs. Ninon MacKnight Smith, December 1964.
- Mr. Apple's Family, by Jean McDevitt. Illustrated by Ninon [MacKnight]., 118pp. 20.5 cm. Page proofs with a few directions in pencil. Unbound. (Box 1)
  A children's book.
  Garden City, New York: The Junior Literary Guild and Doubleday & Company. [c1950].
  Gift of Mrs. Ninon MacKnight Smith. March 1960.
- Mr. Apple's Family, by Jean McDevitt. Illustrated by Ninon [MacKnight]. Los Angeles., ca. 1950.; 5 p.l., 118pp. 20.5 cm. Pencil sketches interspersed with printed text. Publisher's mock-up. (Box 1)
- The Teeny Tiny Woman, by Ninon [MacKnight]. Los Angeles., ca. 1955.; 16 leaves. 16 × 16.5 cm. Original drawings and holograph text. (Box 1)
  A dummy made to submit to publishers. Unpublished.
  Gift of Mrs. Ninon MacKnight Smith, September 1966.
- Illustrations for Bush Holiday by Stephen Fennimore [pseudonym for Dale Collins]. Los Angeles., ca. 1949.; 3 items. Pen and ink sketches. (Box 2)
  Garden City: Doubleday (c1949).
  Gift of Wilbur and Ninon [MacKnight] Smith, 1985.
- Kit Koala: The Shy Little Bear. By Ninon. Los Angeles., ca. 1946-1948.; 10 items, 24 illustrations. Pen and ink. (Box 2)
  Illustrations for the children's story published by Rinehart, 1948. With accompanying correspondence from the publisher, ca. 1946-1948.
  Gift of Mrs. Ninon MacKnight Smith, January 1985.
- Letters from various publishers regarding books illustrated by Ninon MacKnight. v.p., 1961-1971.; 15 items. (Box 2)
  Letters from Doubleday & Company, Incorporated, CBS Records, and children's author, Anne Alexander, concerning books illustrated by Ninon MacKnight. Letter from Doubleday & Company 26 May 1961, is incomplete.
  Gift of Ninon MacKnight Smith, 1985.
- Original watercolor illustrations for The Fairies., 6 items. (Box 2)
  Gift of Paul Jordan Smith, November 1971.
- Sleepy Time. n.p., ca. 1969.; 1 vol., 13 illustrations (Box 2)
  13 watercolor illustrations by Ninon MacKnight [Smith], and a copy of the book published by CBS Books & Records, 1969. Text by Jill Jackson.
  Gift of Wilbur and Ninon Smith, 1985.
- Illustrations for Nathan's Dark House by Florence Bourgeois. Woodland Hills., ca. 1942.; 4 items. Watercolor. (Box 3)
  4 watercolor illustrations for Nathan's Dark House.
  Garden City: Doubleday, Doran & Company [1942].
  Gift of Wilbur and Ninon (MacKnight) Smith, 1985.